good afternoon everybody welcome good to
下午好欢迎大家好
see you hope you all have started your
看到你，希望你 都已经开始了 您
attack lab everybody started be a good
攻击实验室开始大家是个好
time to start I think anyway I hope
时候开始我想反正我希望
you're enjoying it that's a that's a new
你喜欢它 ，这是一个这是一个新的
one this semester that I think really
一个本学期， 我觉得真的
really interesting and modern and
真的很有趣 ，现代和
current okay today we're going to today
今天当前没关系，我们今天会
we're going to talk about something
我们要谈
called the memory hierarchy now so far
现在 叫的存储 层次 到目前为止
in the class we we thought of memory
在课堂上，我们认为，我们的记忆
when we're looking at our assembly
当我们看 我们的组件
language programs we thought of memory
语言课程我们认为的记忆
as a an array of bytes it's a big array
作为一个字节数组 这是一个大数组
of bytes that we can access with an
的字节，我们可以 用一个访问
index called an address but in actuality
指数被称为地址，但实际上
the memory system is a very complex
存储系统是一个非常复杂的
hierarchy of devices that provides this
设备的层次结构提供了这种
abstraction of this this large linear
的这个这个大的线性抽象
array and so today we're going to look
阵列，所以我们今天要去看看
at how memory hierarchies are built and
在存储层次结构如何构建和
why they're built the way they are and
为什么他们建立他们的方式和
and what we'll see is that the sort of
而我们可以看到的是，那种
beautiful confluence of the properties
属性的美丽融合
of storage devices and the properties of
的存储设备和的性质
programs come together to create this
程序来共同创造这个
this this this beautiful design called a
这这这 美丽的设计被称为
memory hierarchy so we're going to
存储层级，所以我们要
quickly kind of do a high-level tour of
很快样做的一个高层次的旅游
storage technologies and trends we're
存储技术和发展趋势我们
not going to go into a whole lot of
不打算进入一大堆
detail the point the point in looking at
详细点， 看着点
these at these that's that the
这些这些就是这样 的
properties of these technologies is that
这些技术的特性是 ，
there are some fundamental properties
有一些基本属性
that determine their performance and
决定其性能和
their speed and determine limits on
他们的速度和对确定限制
their performance and speed and so I
其性能和速度，所以我
want you to have you know a just some
希望你有你认识的只是一些
high-level idea of what those what those
那些什么什么这些 高层次 的 想法
properties are and then we'll look at a
属性，然后我们将 看看在
property of programs called locality of
叫的地方节目属性
reference and we'll see how that
参考我们将看到如何
locality and the properties of storage
局部性和 存储的 属性
devices come together to suggest this
设备走到一起，表明这
design of memory systems as
存储器系统的设计
as a hierarchy okay so we'll look at
作为一个层次好了，我们来看看
memories first now the the workhorse
回忆第一现在的主力
memory is called a random access memory
内存称为随机存取存储器
or Ram it's traditionally packaged up as
或RAM它的传统打包为
a chip and then you put multiple chips
一个芯片上，然后你把多个芯片
together to form to form your main
一起形成，形成你的主
memory and there's a basic storage unit
内存，并有一个基本的存储单元
called a cell which where each cell
叫这其中每个小区的小区
stores one bit okay now there's there's
存储一个比特还好现在有有
a ram comes in two varieties there's a
公羊有两种类型有一个
SRAM and DRAM and they're distinguished
SRAM和DRAM，他们是杰出的
by the way that those cells are
由这些细胞的方法
implemented so in an SRAM requires it's
在SRAM实现这样要求它的
more complex than a than DRAM it
不是比DRAM更复杂
requires like four to six transistors
像需要四到六个晶体管
per bit whereas DRAM only requires a one
每比特而DRAM只需要一个
transistor okay so you'll see that
晶体管好，所以你会看到，
SRAM's are going to be more expensive
SRAM的将是更加昂贵
lots more expensive because they are
许多更 昂贵的，因为它们 是
more complex each cell is more complex
更复杂的 每个单元 是更复杂
but they're also much faster like ten
但他们也快得多好比十个
order of magnitude faster than DRAM and
量级比DRAM 更快
they have a there's some other
他们有一个有一些其他
properties too like SRAM constantly a
性能太像 SRAM一个不断
dram constantly needs to be refreshed if
DRAM需要不断被刷新，如果
you don't hit it with a with a with a
你不带一个带打
voltage it loses a charge whereas DRAM
电压失去电荷，而DRAM
while it needs to be plugged in and and
而它需要被堵塞，并且
have an electric charge it doesn't need
有一电一充不需要
to be refreshed SRAM is a lot more
要刷新SRAM是 一个很大的
reliable than DRAM so it there's less
比DRAM可靠，因此有较少
need for error detection and correction
需要检错 和 纠错
and there and so because of this
还有等等，因为这
difference right the SRAM's are costlier
差异右边的SRAM的是昂贵的
smaller and faster than DRAM we find
而小于DRAM 我们 更快 找到
SRAM's being used in these small fast
SRAM在这些小快被使用
memories on on chip called cache
片上称为高速缓冲存储器上
memories and we're going to learn all
回忆我们要学习所有
about those on Thursday and then DRAM is
那些在星期四，然后是DRAM
the workhorse used in main memories and
在主存储器使用的主力和
the frame buffers associated with
相关联的帧缓冲器
graphics graphics cards
图形显卡
now DRAM and SRAM are volatile in the
现在DRAM和SRAM是易失性
sense that if if they're powered off
就是说如果如果他们断电
they they lose all the information right
他们他们失去了所有的信息的权利
so this is why when you turn your
所以这就是 为什么当你打开你
computer off you have to you lose
关闭电脑，你必须 你失去
everything in your memory and you have
一切都在你的记忆， 你有
to when you turn it back on you have to
当你打开它 ， 你 必须
sort of reload everything from from your
那种 从 重装所有的东西 你
disk there's a different kind of memory
盘有一个不同类型的内存
called a non-volatile memory which
称为非易失性存储器，其
retains its information when it's
保留其信息时，它的
powered off and there's a whole bunch of
断电， 还有 的一大堆
these things that so-called a read-only
这些东西是所谓的一个只读的
memory so the generic name for these
内存因此， 对这些通用名称
non-volatile memories is read only
非易失性存储器是只读
memories or roms and there's a whole
回忆或ROM和有一个整体
bunch of different kinds sort of going
很多不同 类型 的 排序会
back in time
时光倒流
the original read only memories were
只有原读取记忆是
roms and they can only do program once
ROM和他们只能做一次程序
when the chip was was produced and then
当被制作的芯片，然后
over time gradually over a period of
随着时间的推移逐渐在一段
like twenty or thirty years there were
像 二三十年有
improvements in the way that Rob's could
在方式罗布的可能改进
be programmed and in how they were
在他们如何进行编程和
erased so they could be reprogrammed the
删除。 因此，它们可以 被重新编程
what we have today the the modern form
我们今天 的 现代 形式
of read only memories is called flash
的只读存储器被称为闪光
memory which provides the capability of
存储器，其提供的能力
erasing you can erase just chunks of the
删除您可以删除刚才的块
flash memory called blocks and then the
闪存称为块，然后将
the downside is that these things wear
不足之处是这些东西 穿
out after about a hundred thousand
出来后 约十万
erasers okay so you can erase and
橡皮擦好了，你可以擦除并
reprogram a hundred thousand times and
改编十万次，
then and then it's your bricked now that
然后，然后它是你的砖砌现在
these non-volatile memories are show up
这些非易失性存储器的出现
in Inwood so-called firmware which is
在伍德 所谓固件是
software that's that's programmed into
这是一个的编入软件
it into Iran and you see those in the
它进入伊朗 ，你看到那些 在
bios of computers so when you power on
电脑的BIOS，所以当你开机
your computer the very first
您的计算机中的第一个
instructions that execute are stored in
其执行存储在指令
a in a ROM right if you're wondered like
一个在右，如果你想知道像 ROM
where do those things come from so
哪里来的这么那些事
they're stored in ROM and then there's a
他们存储在ROM中，然后有一个
boot process where gradually more and
启动过程，其中渐渐地
more information is and instructions are
更多的信息和指令
loaded into memory
加载到内存
you know IO IO devices have little
你知道IO IO设备几乎没有
computers in them called controllers
在他们的计算机被称为控制器
these controllers consist of
这些控制器包括
instructions and data that are that are
指令和数据 是被
stored in roms and you see them all over
存储在ROM 和你在一饱眼福
and all over the place in these solid
并且 遍布 在这些坚实的地方
state disks that to the to the to the
固态盘是到到到
system look like a rotating disk but
系统看起来就像一个旋转的磁盘，但
they're built of flash memories and
他们正在建造的快闪记忆体和
these are you see these in thumb drives
这些都是你的拇指 驱动器看到这些
smartphones tablets and laptops and
智能手机平板电脑和笔记本电脑和
they're even starting to show up in in
他们甚至开始 在 露面
servers now so the memories are
服务器现在这样的记忆
connected to the CPU using sort of wires
连接到使用排序 线的 CPU
that are collectively called buses okay
被统称为公交车好吗
so data flows across the wires back and
所以数据跨越导线流回和
forth from the we have the CPU chip and
提出从我们的CPU芯片和
it consists of a register file these are
它由一个寄存器文件这些都是
the general-purpose registers are ax RDI
通用寄存器是 斧子RDI
and so on and there's an arithmetic
等等，并有一个算术
logic unit that reads and writes data
逻辑单元，其读取和写入数据
from the register files and then
从寄存器文件，然后
manipulates that data in some way by
操纵以某种方式通过数据
doing some kind of arithmetic operation
做某种类型的 算术运算
or some logical operation and if
或一些逻辑操作，并且如果
instructions if instructions need to
说明如果指令需要
access memory so if there's you're doing
存取存储器 所以如果有你做
a move a move instruction that reads or
此举移动指令读取或
writes to memory then that's handled by
写入到内存中，然后多数民众赞成通过处理
a bus interface which is connected to a
被 连接到一个 总线接口
what we'll call a system bus and then
我们就这么叫系统总线，然后
that's connected to an i/o bridge and
其是连接到一个I / O桥与
this this is another collection of chips
这这是芯片 的另一集合
Intel calls this what I'm calling a i/o
英特尔称这 是一种我称为 AI / O
Bridge they call the chipset okay but
桥他们称该芯片组 还可以，但
it's a collection of chips separate from
它的芯片集合从分离
the process the CPU chip and then the
过程中的CPU芯片，然后将
i/o bridge is connected to another bus
I / O桥被连接 到另一个 总线
called the memory bus which which
所谓存储器总线其中这
connects the main memory you know this
连接你知道这个 主存储器
is uh this is kind of an abstraction I
是呵，这 是 一种抽象的我
don't want you to take this too
不想你把这太
literally but it it gives you the idea
从字面上但它给你的 想法
of how information flows in the system
的信息在系统中如何流动
okay modern modern systems use
还好摩登现代的系统使用
proprietary bus designs and they're very
专用总线设计和他们非常
very arcane and increasingly complex so
非常神秘 和日益复杂，所以
we're just going to we're just going to
我们只是要我们正要
use a fairly simple abstraction for for
使用了一个非常简单的抽象
these sub for these butts architectures
这些 子这些烟头 架构
now when is now suppose you do a load
现在现在当假设你做一个负载
operation like move move queue the eight
像移动移动操作排队八
bytes at address a into our ax okay so
个字节地址到 我们的斧子 好了，
we call that a load because we're we're
我们称之为负载，因为我们是我们
loading from from the point of view of
从从视图的点装
the CPU we're loading data into the the
在CPU我们将数据装载到了
CPU but we're loading and we're loading
CPU，但我们正在加载，我们正在加载
data from memory into the CPU so when
来自存储器的数据到CPU，以便当
when the CPU executes the move
当CPU 执行招
instruction like this it first places
这样的指令，它第一个地方
the address of a on the memory bus and
的存储器总线上的地址和
then the main main memory senses that
然后主主存储器感测到
address and it reads the contents the
解决和读出内容的
eight bytes at address a so it retrieves
在地址的八个字节，因此检索
the word eight byte word from address a
从地址字一个八字节的字
and places it back on the bus
并把它回到了巴士
the those bits travel through the i/o
的那些位行进通过I / O
bridge to the bus interface and then the
桥的总线接口，然后
the CPU reads that the word X from the
CPU读取从字X
data word X from the bus and then
从总线， 然后数据字X
competent into register Ras okay so it's
主管到寄存器的Ras 好了，所以它的
now writing is is is similar again so
现在写的 是类似于再 这样
here we're doing a move instruction move
在这里，我们正在做一个移动指令移动
q from our ax in to address a in main
从我们的斧头● 在解决 一个主
memory okay so the the CPU start as
内存没关系所以CPU的开端，
before by placing the address a on the
之前通过将地址上
bus main memory reads that address and
总线主存储器中读取该地址和
then it waits for the data to arrive on
然后等待数据 到达上
the bus so the CPU then places the
公交所以CPU 然后将 这些
contents of our a X on the bus those
总线那些对我们的健康X的内容
contents travel across to main memory
内容分布在主内存旅行
which then reads the reads that word
然后读取读取字
from the bus and stores it at address a
从总线将它保存在地址
okay so the the point of all this is
好了，所以在 这一切的一点是
that operations that occur you know
该发生的，你知道的操作
reads and writes of registers because
读取和寄存器写入，因为
the register file is very close to the
寄存器文件是非常接近
ALU these happen in on the order of a
ALU这些发生在 一个 数量级上
few cycles
几个周期
okay register the regice
还好注册regice
it's very close to the to the ALU so
这是非常接近 的ALU如此
those operations are very happened very
这些操作都是非常非常事
quickly whereas memories actually this
快速而回忆 其实这
is a set of chips that are very far away
是一组很远芯片
relatively speaking from the CT you can
从CT相对来说，你可以
there's a lot going on in when if you
有很多事情在的时候，如果你
have to read or write memory there's it
要读取或写入内存有它
you have to do multiple operations on
你必须做多操作
the bus data has to travel propagate
总线数据有旅行繁殖
across that bus all this stuff takes
跨总线所有这些东西需要
time so memory operations reads and
时间，存储操作和读取
writes are typically you know maybe 50
写通常，你知道，也许50
nanoseconds 100 nanoseconds whereas
纳秒100纳秒，而
operations that occur between registers
寄存器之间发生的操作
are sub nanosecond okay on the order so
在亚纳秒没关系的 顺序，从而
you're talking about a 1 to 2 orders of
你在谈论一个1至2个 数量级的
magnitude difference if you have to go
如果你必须去 幅度差
off chip 2 to retrieve something from
关闭芯片2检索来自东西
memory ok so that's the first sort of
内存 好了，所以 这是第一个排序的
big takeaway item about memory systems
关于内存的系统大外卖项目
now another popular storage technology
现在另一种流行的存储技术
is rotating disks and I don't know if
旋转磁盘和我不知道
you've ever torn one apart they're kind
你曾经撕开一个除了他们亲切
of interesting there's a series of
有趣的还有一系列
platters each platter is coated with a
盘片每个盘片涂覆有
magnetic material and then bits ones and
磁性材料，然后位一和
zeros are encoded in that in that
零进行编码，在这
magnetic material and then there's this
磁性材料，然后有这个
arm that can it's it's hinged right here
可它就是它的铰链 在 这里手臂
and then it can it can it floats over
然后它可以在 它 可以 在浮动
the platter so it floats on a thin layer
盘片 所以它漂浮在 薄层
of air over the platter and there's a
空气在大盘 子 ，有一个
read/write head at the very end that can
在最后，可以读/写头
sense the changes in the magnetic field
感应磁场的变化
that encode the disk okay so these
并且编码 盘 好了，所以这些
platters are spinning around like like
盘片的旋转周围像像
counterclockwise like this and this this
逆时针这样 ，和本
arm can go back and forth so there's a
手臂可以来回走 所以有
lot of mechanical gear so this is all
大量的机械 传动 的 ，所以这是所有
mechanical so the mechanical nature of a
机械左右的 机械性质
rotating disc needs it's going to be
旋转 盘 需要它的将是
slower right then then D Rams and NS
较慢的右则则D RAM和NS
Rams and there's also electronics like
公羊还有还有像电子
it's like a little computer in firmware
它就像一个在固件中的小计算机
that that actually controls the the
这实际控制的
operation of this drive like controls
此驱动器等的控制的操作
how this
如何
arm goes back and forth and and and
手臂往返和和和
controls how the data is read off of the
控制数据是如何读出的
read/write head so just in a little more
只是多一点的读/写头，
detail we can think of these disks
我们可以认为 这些磁盘的 细节
consists of platters each platter has
由盘片每个盘片具有
two services the top and the bottom and
两个服务的顶部和底部 ，
then each surface consists of these
然后每个表面由这些
transfers are concentric rings called
接送同心圆称为
tracks and then each track consists of
跟踪，然后将每个轨道包括
us it consists of sectors which contain
我们是由含有部门
the data
数据
so typically 512 512 bits or I'm sorry
所以通常512 512位或对不起
bytes and and then except these tracks
字节，然后除这些轨道
are separated by gaps that goat that
通过 山羊该间隙被分开
these gaps like right here that don't
这些差距好像就在我不
contain now data now platters are
现在包含现在的数据是盘片
aligned on top of each other on top on
对 顶部在彼此的顶部对齐
this spindle and so tracks that are
该主轴等的轨道是
aligned on the different surfaces such
不同 的 表面 ，例如上对齐
as this track here on those the
因为这里与这条赛道
collection of those tracks formal we
这些曲目正式我们的集合
call a cylinder okay because it has a
打电话好吗缸，因为它有一个
cylindrical shape now the capacity of
现在圆筒形的容量
disks is that the number of bits that
磁盘是该 比特数
can be stored and vendors kind of they
可以存储和供应商样，他们的
all dis vendors use that they quote the
所有DIS厂商使用他们的报价
capacity in gigabytes but where a
在千兆字节的容量，但 其中一个
gigabyte is 10 to the ninth bytes right
千兆字节是10至第九字节右
instead of 2 to the 20th okay like like
而不是2到20 好喜欢喜欢
you would expect so what it I'm not sure
你会想到那么什么我不 知道
why they do this but it allows by by
他们为什么这样做，但它允许通过
quoting their capacity and gigabytes in
引用他们的能力和千兆字节
ten to the ninth bytes it it's a bigger
十到第九个字节它， 它是一个更大的
number right so it looks better it looks
数 右所以看起来它看起来越好
like there's more information it's a
像有更多的信息，这是一个
little I don't really know why they do
小我真的不知道 他们 为什么 这样做
it but I think that's why it is and it's
但我认为 ，这就是为什么它是和它的
so it's one of those little bit of
所以它的 那些点点之一
annoying things that we just have to
恼人的事情， 我们 只需要
just know about and get used to now the
只知道现在的习惯
capacity is determined by two
容量由两个确定
independent technology factors one is
独立的技术因素之一是
the recording density so that's how many
记录密度所以这是多少
bits can you pack into a single sector
位可以装进单个扇区
or for us or at least a portion of the
或我们或至少 的 一部分
other track and then the track density
其它轨道，然后将磁道密度
which is sort of how close can you put
这是那种你如何接近可以把
those tracks together and then the
这些曲目在一起 ，然后将
product of those two is what's called
这两个产品是所谓
the areal density and that determines
面密度以及确定
the overall capacity of the disc so the
光盘的 总 容量 ，因此
higher the areal capacity the more bits
更高的面容量的多个比特
you can squeeze on to that onto that
你可以挤在到该上
surface now in the old days when aerial
现在表面昔日的空中时，
densities were fairly low each each
密度是相当低的每各
track on the surface would have the same
赛道表面上会具有相同的
number of sectors okay so there was a
扇区数好了，所以出现了
constant number of sectors per track so
每个磁道的扇区 ，以便 恒定数
now what happens as you as your tracks
现在你会发生什么作为你的曲目
go from the you know near near the whole
从靠近你知道整个去附近
by the spindle as they go as they move
由主轴，因为他们去，因为他们移动
outward right if you have the same
如果你也有同样的权利向外
number of sectors with the same with the
部门与在相同数量的
same track bit density that the gaps
相同的轨道位密度，所述间隙
between sectors are going to get bigger
部门之间会得到更大
and bigger as you go out and you're
和更大的作为你出去你
going to be wasting more and more of
将要浪费更多的
your of your space so at when aerial
你的空间，让你在空中时
densities were fairly low this was okay
密度是相当低的，这是好的
but after a while it just became not
但 经过一段时间它只是变得不
okay to waste that much room so what
好浪费那么多空间，所以什么
modern systems do is they they partition
现代系统做的是他们，他们分区
the tracks into these so called rook
轨道到这些所谓的 车
recording zones where each each
记录区域，其中每个各
recording zone such as this right here
记录区 像这样的就在这里
each recording zone has a constant
每个记录区具有恒定
number of sectors so each track in a
扇区的数量，以便在每个轨道
recording zone has the same number of
记录区具有相同数量的
sectors and of course as you move
部门，当然，当您移动
outward if you move outward in the
向外如果在向外移动
recording zone you're going to have
记录带你将有
bigger and bigger gaps but then but then
越做越大的差距，但随后却对
you start a new recording zone that will
你开始一个新的记录区即会
have more sectors per track and then
有每磁道 ，然后 更多的扇区
within that
内
so you can see in this outer in this
所以你可以在这个在外在这看
outer zone you have more you have more
你有外区的越多，你有更多的
sectors than you do on this inner zone
行业比你做这个内区
okay so that's a way to kind of deal
好了，这是一个办法来样 交易
with that sort of that that that growth
与那种认为这 是成长
in the gaps to keep it from getting too
在间隙保持它变得太
large and so because we don't really
大，是 因为我们 真的不
have the number of sectors per track
有 每磁道 的扇区数
isn't constant we'll use an average the
是不是恒定的，我们将使用一个平均的
average sectors per track across all
平均每个部门追踪所有
recording zones when we do sort of our
记录区的时候，我们做排序 的我们
capacity estimates okay so you can
容量估算 好了，你可以
imagine the formula for computing the
想象的公式 计算所述
disk capacity is fairly straightforward
磁盘容量是相当简单
it's the number of bytes per sector
它的每扇区字节数
times the average number of sectors per
平均 每扇区倍
track times the average number of tracks
追踪时代 音轨的平均数
per surface times the number of surfaces
面的每面的次数
per platter times the number of platters
盘片的单碟次数
per disk okay now let's look at how just
每个磁盘现在没事了，让我们看看 如何只
work so these these surfaces are
工作，所以这些这些表面
spinning at a fixed rotational rate now
以固定旋转速率现在纺丝
a typical rate may be 7200 rpm is a
一个典型的速率 可以是7200转是一个
fairly common rotational rate so the
相当普遍的旋转速率，因此
disk is spinning around you can see this
盘转圈，你可以看到这
pretty proud of that
很骄傲的说
so it's spinning around a counter
所以它围绕旋转的反
clockwise and then the arm moves
顺时针然后 臂移动
radially here we go
径向这里我们去
the arm moves radially and it can go
手臂径向运动，它可以去
over any of the tracks okay all right
在任何轨道 还好没事
that's enough okay now when you have
现在这已经足够好了，当你有
multiple platters each one of these each
多个盘片每个这些每一个
one of these there's actually multiple
其中一个有实际多
arms and there's a read/write head on
武器和有一个 读/写头
each surface so if the platters has to -
每个表面，所以如果盘片具有 -
if to each side of the platter is coated
如果对 盘片的 每一侧 被 涂覆
with this magnetic material then you'll
这种磁性材料 那么你会
have you have a read/write head on each
有你对每一个读/写磁头
side and then these are all connected
侧，然后将这些都 连接
they kind of moved together
他们那种一起移动
now originally they these read/write
现在原来他们这些读/写
heads would be they were rigid right
头是他们的权利刚性
because the densities track densities
因为密度的磁道密度
weren't that high so they could they
不高，因此他们可能他们
could just sort of licks and even though
可能只是 有点乐句和即使
the tracks didn't line perfectly now
轨道不完美 ，现在 排队
they could just sort of they could they
他们可能只是排序他们的，他们可能
could still cover the the read/write
仍然可以覆盖读 /写
heads could still cover the tracks with
头仍然可以覆盖轨道
these fixed with these fixed arms but
这些固定这些固定的武器，但
nowadays that that the densities are so
时下的密度 是如此
high that they actually the controller
高，他们其实控制器
can actually move the read/write heads a
实际上可以移动的读/写头一个
little bit so that it matches up with
点点，使其 与相匹配
that all of the tracks on all of the
所有的轨道上所有的
surfaces okay so let's look at how this
表面好了，让我们来看看如何
works how we read data so we have our
作品我们如何读取数据，所以我们有我们的
this is our this is our arm and the tip
这是我们的，这是我们的手臂 和尖端
of the arrow is the read/write head and
箭头的是读/写头和
it's positioned and the platter is
它的定位和盘片是
rotating counterclockwise and it's
逆时针旋转，它的
positioned just ready to read the blue
定位刚准备读取蓝
sector so it as the blue sector spins
部门因此它为蓝色部门自旋
underneath the read/write head it senses
该读/写头的下方其感测
those bits and sends them up to the
这些比特，并将它们发送到
controller which passes them back up to
控制器，其将它们传递回至
the CPU and now the CPU is requested
CPU和现在的CPU要求
that the disk it's requested the red
磁盘 它要求红
data from the red sector so we have to
从红色部门的数据，所以我们必须
take the controller takes that
取控制器采取该
read/write head moves it back to red
读/写磁头移回 红
track
跟踪
and then waits for it to spin around and
然后等待它左右旋转和
to the to the read/write head and then
在读/写头，然后
it reads that that red that red sector
它读取红色红色 部门
okay so when we first so there's really
好了，所以当 我们第一次如此没什么
three components going on here that
三个组件 会在这里 说
determine how long it takes to read one
确定需要多长时间来读取一个
of these sectors the when we move the
这些部门的当我们移动
head
头
that's called a seek when we waited for
这就是所谓的寻找，当我们等待
the red track to to sort of rotate
红色轨道排序的旋转
around that's called the rotational
围绕这就是所谓的旋转
latency so however long it takes on
延迟，所以但需要多长时间上
average it will be half of the half of
平均它将是一半的一半
the time it takes for the entire to
它需要 整个 的 时间
circle all the way around and then
周围再绕一路
there's the data transfer which is sort
有这类型的数据传输
of how long it takes for that for that
多长时间需要为为
track to pass under the read/write head
跟踪读/写磁头下方通过
now the reason the reason it's important
现在的原因的原因是很重要的
to know this is that these three
要知道这是这三个
components you add them together and
组件添加它们放在一起，
that's the that's what your average time
这就是这就是你的平均 时间
it takes to access data that time is
它需要的是时间访问数据
dominated by the seek time so seek times
由寻道时间占据如此寻道时间
are measured in milliseconds right so
以毫秒为单位被测量对好
we're moving this head there's this
我们正在这头有这
there's a servo that has to fire up and
有有火起来 的伺服 和
there's actual mechanical motion and
有实际的机械运动和
that that takes time and it's on the
这需要时间，它是在
order of three to nine milliseconds and
3到9毫秒秩序
this has been true for decades right so
这一直是真正的几十年这样的权利
this this value is not changing right
这个这个值是不会改变 的权利
there's just sort of fundamental
还有的根本只是排序
mechanical limits that make it very
机械极限，使得它非常
difficult to to decrease this this value
难以降低这此值
now the rotational latency the time that
现在旋转延迟 的时间
it takes to spin around will we'll call
它需要不停地旋转 会我们会打电话给
that the T average rotation and then the
的 T平均旋转，然后 将
time it takes to read the bits will call
花费的时间读这些位将调用
T average transfer okay so we have T
牛逼平均传输好了，所以我们个人有T
average seek which is this seek time
平均寻道时间是这个 寻道时间
rotational latency and transfer time and
旋转等待时间和传送时间和
now if we just take some typical numbers
现在，如果我们只是 把一些 典型的数字
and plug those in you see that our seek
和插在那些你看到我们寻求
time is on the order of milliseconds the
时间是毫秒的量级
rotational rate is also on the order of
旋转速度也量级
milliseconds right so there's there's
毫秒权利，使有有
also mechanical limits and how fast you
同时机械极限的速度有多快你
can you can spin these around the access
你可以可以旋转这些周围 的访问
time and the transfer the transfer time
时间和传输的 传输时间
is very small so it's orders of
非常小，所以 它的订单
magnitude smaller because you just you
幅度要小，因为你就是你
just have to read a few the bits that
只 需要读几个比特
are in one sector okay so if you if you
在一个行业好，所以如果你，如果你
look you can you can see that the total
看你能，你可以看到总
access time is dominated by seek and
访问时间是寻求和主导
rotational latency so you know a good
旋转延迟，所以你知道的好
rule of thumb just for sort of
只是有点经验法则
estimating how long it takes to read
估计需要多长时间阅读
from a disk is just take twice the seek
从谋求盘只取两次
the seek time and you'll be you'll be
寻道时间，你会你会
pretty close and basically the transfer
相当接近，基本上转移
time is you get that for free now here's
时间就是你得到的是免费的，现在这里的
the here's the important thing to know
在这里要知道 最重要的事情
about disks we SRAM access times about
有关磁盘我们在SRAM约访问时间
four nanoseconds to get a double word
4纳秒得到 一个双字
DRAM is about 60 nanoseconds so DRAM is
DRAM是大约60纳秒所以DRAM是
about an order of magnitude slower than
约一个数量级慢
SRAM but disk is 40,000 times slower
SRAM但盘 慢40000次
than SRAM so that's 4,000 orders of
比SRAM所以这是4000个订单
magnitude difference that's huge and
幅度差 这是巨大的和
it's it's 250 times orders of magnitude
这是它的幅度的 250倍订单
slower than T Rams so the the there's a
且T公羊慢，因此在有一个
big gap between DRAM and SRAM and
DRAM和SRAM之间差距较大
there's an even bigger gap between disk
有盘之间更大的差距
and and other other memory types
和等其它存储器类型
now modern disks present a much simpler
现在现代磁盘呈现更简单
view than so we then this this track
鉴于比，所以我们那么这这条赛道
cylinder sector geometry so modern
缸部门几何，所以现代
modern disk controllers actually present
现代磁盘控制器实际存在
to the CPU they present the disk is a
到 CPU它们呈现该盘是
sequence of logical blocks where each
逻辑块的序列，其中每个
block is is a multiple of a sector side
块是是扇区 侧 的倍数
so this in the simplest case the block
因此这在最简单的情况下，块
is just think of a logical block is one
只是觉得一个逻辑块是一个
sector and then blocks are
扇区，然后块
starting at zero and they just go all
从零开始， 他们只是全力以赴
the way up to some to some large number
向上一些一些 大量 方式
and then the the disk controller keeps
然后将磁盘控制器保持
the mapping maintains the mapping
映射保持映射
between logical blocks and the actual
逻辑块与实际之间
physical sectors so as as in the old
物理扇区，从而为老
saying is you know most most interesting
说的是你知道最有趣最
ideas in computer science are involve
在 计算机科学的想法是涉及
some form of indirection so this is a
某种形式的间接的，所以这是一个
level of indirection that provides you
间接的水平，为您提供
know this mapping between logical blocks
知道的逻辑块之间的这种映射
and physical blocks so it allows disk
和物理块因此它允许磁盘
controllers to take some cylinders and
控制器采取一些汽缸和
reserve them as spare cylinders that
保留他们作为备用气瓶 那
aren't mapped in e logical blocks and
在电子逻辑块没有被映射和
then if there's if one of the sectors
那么，如果有如果的部门之一
goes bad in a cylinder that the disk
在气缸磁盘变坏
controller can can just copy copy the
控制器可以只复制 复制
data over to a spare cylinder and then
到备用筒，然后数据
just keep going right so this and so
只是不停权利，使这一点，所以
this is why your 4matic capacity is is
这就是为什么你的 4MATIC 容量是
less than sort of the if you know if you
不到排序的，如果你知道，如果你
counted the number of actual cylinders
算实际的气缸 数
on the disk
在磁盘上
the 4matic capacity is less than the
所述4MATIC 容量小于
maximum capacity because some of those
最大容量，因为一些人的
cylinders are being reserved for
汽缸被保留以供
failures now devices like disks are
故障现在如磁盘设备
connected to the to the CPU and the
连接到所述CPU和所述
memory via the i/o bridge over another
经由I / O桥的另一个存储器
kind of bus called an i/o bus this what
一种总线称为I / O总线这是什么
I'm showing you what I'm showing you now
我显示你有什么我 展示你现在
is is actually not representative of
是实际上是不具有代表性的
modern systems it's representative of
现代系统是典型的
what was called the PCI bus about five
什么是所谓的PCI总线大约五
years ago modern buses now are the PCI
年前，现代客车现在的PCI
bus is a broadcast bus meaning it's just
总线是广播总线意味着它只是
a single set of wires so if any device
单组导线，所以如果任何设备
changes the values on those wires every
改变这些导线中的值每
device on that bus can see those values
该总线上的设备可以看到这些值
okay that's called the broadcast bus and
还好这就是所谓 的广播总线和
it's a simplest kind of way to hook
这是一个最简单的一种方式挂钩
things together modern systems use a bus
事堂现代生产系统采用总线
structure called PCI Express which
结构称为PCI Express的这
although it has the word PCI and it's
虽然它有 字PCI和 它的
completely different it's point-to-point
完全不同的是点至点
so devices are connected by a set of
这样的设备是由一组连接
point-to-point connections
点对点连接
arbitrated by uh by some kind of a
通过呃仲裁通过 某种形式 的
switch and we won't go into it it's the
切换，我们不会进入 它 它的
same idea it's a much more efficient
同样的 想法这是一个更有效
design it's much faster and but it
设计它的速度更快，但它
provides the same capability mainly it
主要提供同样的功能它
just attaches up it allows you to attach
只是接了它可以让 你连接
all of your devices to your to your CPU
所有设备你 到你的 CPU
so just think of this bus as this sort
所以才觉得这个总线作为这种
of a single set of wires where each wire
单组导线，其中每个导线
carries a bit and every device attached
携带位和连接的每一个设备
to it can see all the values of all the
它可以看到所有的所有的值
wires and so it there's some devices
电线，所以它 有一些设备
that are just built it directly into the
这只是建造它直接进入
motherboard and they attach to the bus
主板和 他们连接到总线
like you know disk to just plug directly
像你知道磁盘只是直接插入
into sockets on a motherboard and you
进入主板，您对插座
know your graphics adapter and the USB
知道你的图形适配器和USB
controller and then the system presents
控制器，然后系统呈现
an interface so you can plug mouse
一个界面， 您可以插入 鼠标
things like Mouse's mice and keyboards
之类的老鼠的鼠标和键盘
into the USB controller and then there's
插入USB控制器 ，然后 有
expansion slots that allow you that
扩展槽允许您
connect to the wires and in the bus that
连接到导线，并在总线
allow you to add other devices like
允许您添加其他设备，如
maybe networking oh if you want to put a
也许联网哦，如果你想要把一个
network adapter in there now what
在有网络适配器现在该怎么办
happens when we want to read a disk
发生在我们想要读取磁盘
sector well the CPU initiates this read
部门以及CPU的启动这个读
by writing a triple so it writes three
通过写一个三重所以编写三种
different values it writes a command
不同的值写入一个命令
like say read it writes a logical block
好比说读取写入逻辑块
number so I want to read a logical block
数，所以我想读逻辑块
number and I want to place the contents
号码，我希望把内容
of that logical block at a certain
在一定的那个逻辑块的
address in memory okay so it's a command
在内存中处理好所以它是一个命令
logical block number and a memory
逻辑块号和一个存储器
address the disk controller reads the
解决磁盘控制器读取
whatever sector corresponds to that
任何部门对应于
logical block so we'll assume that
逻辑块所以我们假设
logical blocks are consists of one
逻辑块是由一个的
sector and then it does this interesting
扇区，然后它这个有趣
thing it copies it takes control of the
事情 它复制它需要的控制
bus and it copies the data this is the
公交车，并将其复制的数据是这样的
disk controller now copies the data
磁盘控制器现在复制数据
across the i/o bus through the i/o
横跨通过I I / O总线/ O
bridge and directly to main memory
桥梁和直接到主存
without ever notifying the CPU so the
而不会通知的CPU，因此
CPU is complete
CPU完成
the oblivious to the fact that this
在 无视事实，这
transfer is going on and then once it's
转移是怎么回事 ，然后一旦它
once it's transferred the data it's a
一旦它传输的数据是一个
main memory then it notifies the CPU
主存储器然后它通知CPU
using this mechanism called an interrupt
使用这种机制称为中断
so it actually asserts a pin on the the
因此它实际上声称在该引脚
actual CPU chip itself so it changes the
实际的CPU芯片本身，以便它改变了
value of that pin from 0 to 1 and that
该引脚的值从0到1， 并且
trigger is an interrupt and which
扳机是一个中断，并且
notifies the CPU that that that that
通知CPU认为这是该
sector has been copied ok so then the
部门已 确定 复制 这样则
CPU if there's some program somewhere
CPU，如果有一些程序某处
waiting for that data to be read into
等待数据读入
memory so now now the CPU can can
内存 所以现在现在的CPU 可以可以
execute that program and deal with that
执行该程序并处理该
memory so what this what this mechanism
内存中，因此这是什么这是什么 机制
allows and the reason they do this is
允许他们这样做的原因是
because this there's just so god-awful
因为 这里面只是 这么神可怕的
slow the within 10 milliseconds a system
减缓在10毫秒内 的系统
could be executing millions and millions
可以执行数以百万计
of instructions the CPU could be
指令的CPU 可
executing millions of millions of
执行百万千万的
instructions it will be a terrible waste
说明这将是一个可怕的 浪费
that the CPU waited for that data to
该CPU等待该数据来
come off the disk so what it does is it
脱落的磁盘，这样它的作用是它
it issues this request to the disk
它发出这个请求磁盘
controller and then while that well that
控制器 ，然后而清楚
really slow laborious process is going
真的很慢艰苦的过程是怎么回事
on the CPU can be executing other
在CPU上可以执行的其他
instructions and during the other useful
指令和在其他有用
work so this is really essential to sort
工作，所以这真的是必不可少的 排序
of getting reasonable performance and
的越来越合理的性能 和
from keeping this really slow disk
从保持这种很慢的磁盘
system from slowing the system down
从系统拖慢系统
now there's another interesting hype
现在有另一个有趣的 炒作
kind of disc called a solid-state disk
光盘类型称为 固态硬盘
which is kind of halfway between
这是一种中途 之间
rotating rotating disks and a dram
旋转旋转盘 和 DRAM
memories and a solid-state disk to the
回忆和固态硬盘到
to the CPU it looks exactly like a
到 CPU，它看起来酷似
rotating disk it has the same socket
旋转盘具有相同的插座
plug it has the same physical interface
插上它具有相同的物理接口
that has the same packaging okay it
具有相同的包装还行 吧
looked like a rotating disc but instead
看起来像一个旋转的圆盘，而是
of having all these mechanical
具有 所有这些机械 的
it's actually built entirely out of
它实际上完全是建出来的
flash memory and firmware that acts as
闪存和 固件 作为
the the controller so inside of a
所述控制器，以便 的 内部
solid-state disk there's a firmware a
固态硬盘有一个固件
set of firmware called the flash
固件的一套名为闪光
translation layer which serves the
其用于所述转换层
purpose as the same purpose as the disk
目的， 同一目的的 磁盘
controller does in a rotating disc the
控制器确实 在旋转 盘的
and then the memory itself the read data
然后存储器本身读出的数据
can be read read and written from the
可以读取读取 和写入
flash memory in units of pages which
闪存以页为单位，其
depending on the technology can be 512
取决于技术可为512
Kbytes to 4 K bytes and then a sequence
KB 到4千个字节，然后一个序列
of pages forms a block now these these
页面现在这些这些形式的块
these blocks are different from the
这些块是从不同的
logical blocks that the CPU does so it's
逻辑块的CPU 这样做是
kind of an unfortunate overlap of terms
这类条款的不幸重叠
but the the trick is or the I guess the
但关键是还是我猜
limitation is that data is written in
限制是，数据被写入
units of pages but a page can only be
页为单位，但一个页面只能是
written after the entire block is been
写入 整个块被 后
erased okay so that's that seems kind of
抹去好了，就是 这样似乎有点
weird but that's that's the way it works
奇怪，但就是 这样的工作方式
so what that means is if you want to
所以这是什么意思是，如果你想
write if you want to write to a page you
写，如果你想给 你写信页面
have to find a block somewhere that's
必须找到一个 地方 块 这
been erased you have to copy all of the
被擦除你必须复制所有的
other pages in your in your target block
在您的其他网页 在您的目标块
over to that new block and then you can
到新的块，然后你可以
do the right okay so you can see that
做正确的好，所以你可以 看到，
writes now become fairly complex
写入现在变得相当复杂
operation read you can read anything and
操作读你可以读什么和
then like all flash a so it's kind of an
然后像所有的Flash 一所以它的类型的
efficient right because you're writing
高效正确的，因为你写
one page but to do that you have to sort
一个页面，但 要做到这一点 ， 你必须 排序
of copy all the other pages in that
的拷贝在所有其他网页
block and you have to be race the whole
块，你必须是比赛中的 整体
and then when you finish then you erase
然后当你完成，那么你删除
this block so it can be used for for
这个块，因此它可以被用于为
other writes yes
其他写入 是
so eventually after a hundred thousand
所以最终十万后
repeated rights these wear out now the
重复 这些 权利 现在穿出来
flash translation layer Zin
闪存转换层寻
modern systems do all kinds of fancy
现代系统做各种花式的
proprietary algorithms to sort of extend
专有算法排序的延伸
the life they use cashing and and
生活他们使用兑现和和
various tricks to extend the life of
各种技巧来延长寿命
these SSD so in practice it's not really
这些SSD所以在实践中这不是真的
a problem which I'll show you in a
一个问题，我会告诉你的
second so the performance
第二个这样的表现
characteristics of SSDs now you can
固态硬盘的特性，现在你可以
think of a typical hard drive you might
认为一个典型的 硬盘驱动器 ， 你可能
be able to get you know I mean what if
能够让你知道 我的意思是，如果什么
when I measure them when I measure my
当我衡量他们，当我测量
drives that may be 40 50 megabytes per
驱动器，其可以是每40 50兆字节
second that would be a typical rate
第二，这将是一个 典型的速率
okay these SSDs are 10 times faster than
还好这些SSD 比快10倍
that
那
so for sequential reads you can get
因此对于连续读取，你可以得到
about 500 50 megabytes sequential writes
约500 50兆字节顺序写入
are a little bit slower random access
是有点慢随机访问
whether you're reading or writing is a
不管你是在读或写是
little bit slower than sequential access
有点不是 顺序访问 的速度慢
and as we'll see this is that this is
当我们将看到这是，这是
fairly common if it's in memory systems
如果它在 内存系统中相当普遍
it's almost always better to do things
它几乎总是最好做的事情
sequentially than to jump around and
顺序，而不是 跳跃和
erasing random writes are slower because
擦除随机写入速度较慢，因为
erase erasing takes about a millisecond
删除删除大约需要一毫秒
right so now we're back up to that that
右所以现在我们 备份到该
millisecond range which is which is slow
哪个 是哪个毫秒范围 是慢
and as I mentioned yet if you modify one
和我 没有提到，如果你修改一个
one one page after all the other pages
所有其他网页后一个一个页面
in that block have to be copy now
在该块必须现在复制
earlier SSDs had a huge gap between
早期的SSD 之间产生了巨大差距
random writes and and and sequential
随机写入和和和顺序
leads but they because of sort of
线索，但他们因为某种的
improvements in the flash translation
在闪存转换改进
layer these aren't really that that
层中的这些是不是真的那么说
difference right reading and writing
差异正确阅读 和写作
it's writing is slower but they're doing
它的书写速度较慢，但他们正在 做
all kinds of interesting amazing things
各种有趣的令人惊奇的事情
to get these numbers fairly close
得到这些数字相当接近
ok so art when we have a model of SSDs
确定这样的艺术，当我们有固态硬盘的型号
we really don't need to distinguish
我们并不需要区分
anymore that between reads and writes
再那之间的读取和写入
okay so SSDs because they have no moving
好了，所以固态硬盘，因为他们没有动
parts there the faster they take less
部分有更快他们采取少
power they're more rugged you know which
功率他们更坚固 ，你知道哪些
is why they're good for thumb drives and
就是为什么他们是很好的拇指驱动器和
you know iPods and things like that
你知道iPod播放器之类的东西
but they have this potential to wear out
但他们有这个潜力，穿出来
which could be a problem but in practice
这可能是一个问题 ，但在实践中
it's not for example Intel guarantees
它不是例如英特尔担保
that you can do 128 petabytes of writes
你可以做 的写入128个千兆兆字节
before your SSD is no longer good so
在你的SSD不再那么好
that's a lot of data to write I mean
这是一个很大的数据写我 的意思
think about how many years it would take
想想怎么会多年走
to write that much data and as of 20
写那么多数据，并作为20
2015 as of now there are a lot more
2015年截至目前还有很多更
expensive per byte than rotating disks
比旋转圆盘 昂贵 每字节
so rotating disks are much bigger but
所以旋转磁盘是更大的，但
they're slower SSDs are smaller and
他们是慢的固态硬盘体积较小 ，
they're faster now if you take if you
现在他们更快，如果你需要，如果你
look at the performance characteristics
看性能特点
of these different storage devices
这些不同的存储设备的
relative to CPU over time you get this
相对于CPU随着时间的推移，你得到这个
really interesting graph now this this
非常有趣的图表现在这本
graph shows on the y-axis access time in
曲线图示出了在 y轴上的存取时间
nanoseconds in a log scale okay so each
纳秒数 比例 好了，所以每个
each one of these each change in units
这些在单元中的每个改变每一个
from 1,000 to 10,000 represents a order
从1000到10000表示顺序
of magnitude difference in access time
在 访问时间 幅度差的
on the x axis I plotted time going from
在x轴上 画出我的时间去
1985 to 2015 and then I plotted the 30
2085至15 年，然后我绘制的30
the access time or the cycle time of the
访问时间或的周期时间
access time of the these devices disk
在这些设备的磁盘访问时间
SSD DRAM and SRAM and the cycle time of
SSD DRAM和SRAM和周期时间
processors so let's look at on the
处理器，以便让我们来看看在
bottom we have the cycle time of
底部我们的周期时间
processors over time and what you see is
随着时间的推移处理器和你看到的是什么
it's going down at the sort of
它的下降在sort
exponential rate from 1985 to 2003
指数率1985年 至2003 年
there's there's a doubling basically
有有基本上翻倍
every 18 months or two years
每18个月到两年
and in in clock frequency and a
并且在时钟频率和
resulting having of the cycle time over
的循环时间得到的具有过
this 18-month 2 to 2 year period so this
这18个月的2 至 2年的时间 使这
so what what manufacturers did until
还等什么做了什么，直到厂家
2003 to make their processors faster was
2003 让自己的处理器更快了
they would they would just double the
他们将他们只会加倍
clock frequency they decreased the
时钟频率它们 降低 了
feature size of the chips that they were
他们 是芯片的特征尺寸
making and that would allow them to put
做这将让他们 把
things closer together and then have
事情靠得更近 ，然后有
that and then increase the clock
这一点，再增加 时钟
frequency by a proportional amount now
由 成比例的量的频率现在
this all ended 2003 was an interesting
这一切都结束了2003年是一个有趣的
year in computer history because of this
今年由于 这 台计算机的历史
there's a sort of unfortunate property
有一种不幸财产
that the power that you consume is
那你消耗的功率为
proportional to your frequency okay so
正比于你的频率 好吧，
the more power I mean the higher the
更多的权力我的意思是 越高
frequency the more power you consume by
频率您可以通过消耗更多的功率
2003 the processor that Intel was
2003 英特尔是处理器
getting ready to ship was going to burn
准备 船将要 烧
about 800 watts of power think about 800
约800瓦的功率想想800
watt light bulbs inside your laptop and
你的笔记本电脑内瓦的灯泡和
I actually saw an early prototype of one
我居然看到一个的 早期原型
of these devices and the the heatsink to
这些设备和散热 片到的
absorb the power from the chip was about
吸收功率从芯片约
this big it was about 4 square inches
这个大它是 关于4平方英寸
it's a giant thing just sitting on the
这是一个巨大的 东西只是坐在
motherboard so that's what we what we
主板所以这就是我们什么我们
say is that processor design hit the
说的是 ，处理器设计打
power wall in 2003 they could no longer
2003年电墙，他们再也
just continue to increase clock
只是继续增加时钟
frequencies to to get faster to make
频率以获得更快的使
faster computers and what so what they
速度更快的计算机，什么使他们
had to do after 2003 instead of
有2003，而不是后做
increasing the clock frequency and try
增加时钟频率，并尝试
instead of doubling the clock frequency
代替时钟倍频
they put more processor cores onto the
他们把更多的处理器内核到
chips so now they subdivided a CPU chip
芯片所以现在他们再一个CPU芯片
into individual processor cores each one
成单独的处理器核心每一个
could execute its own instructions
可以执行自己的指令
and then so and by running in parallel
然后所以与通过 并行 运行
you could do more effective work so the
你可以做更有效的工作，所以
effective cycle time could continue to
有效的循环时间可以继续
go down
下去
so what I what I've plotted here on the
所以我什么， 我在 这里 绘制 在
bottom is the effective cycle time so
底部是有效的循环时间，以便
basically the the cycle time divided by
基本循环时间除以
the number of cores so here in 2005 that
核心数量因此在这里2005
the first systems use two cores so now
第一个系统，因此现在使用双核
you can run two independent threads or
你可以运行两个独立的线程或
two independent programs and currently
两个独立的程序，目前
it's about four cores server class
它是关于四核服务器类
systems you can get eight cores and
系统就可以得到8个核心，
there's even some twelve core chips so
甚至还有大约 十二核 芯片使
in the future what's going to happen is
在未来发生了什么事情发生的是
that the clock frequencies are going to
时钟频率会
stay fairly constant so you can see the
保持相当恒定的，所以你可以看到
site you can see the cycle time sir they
现场可以看到周期时间，先生，他们
actually increased a little bit here and
这里实际上增加了一点点，
then they're slowly going down but it's
然后他们慢慢地下降，但它
generally flat and so the only way to
一般 平整 ，所以唯一的办法
really get more performance going
真正得到更多的表现 会
forward is to increase the number of
前锋是增加的数量
independent cores and that's just that's
独立内核，这只是这
just the way it's got to be now here in
只是方式它有现在是 在 这里
the the black circle the second line I
所述黑色圆圈的第二行我
plotted the access time for SRAM over
绘制的访问时间在SRAM
time and you can see that SRAM is
时间，你可以看到，SRAM是
tracking CPU pretty good and there's
跟踪CPU非常好 ，有
it's an order of magnitude slower but
这是一个数量级的速度较慢，但
it's tracking the CPU performance pretty
这是非常跟踪CPU性能
well
好
DRAM you can see there's a huge gap
DRAM 可以看到有一个巨大的缺口
between the CPU and the DRAM several
在CPU 和 DRAM 之间 的几个
orders of magnitude and in the last few
在过去的 几年级和订单
years derails have gotten a little
几年出轨已经变得有点
better but they've proven surprisingly
更好，但他们已经证明了出奇
difficult to to make faster SSDs are
很难做出更快的固态硬盘
kind of in between disks and DRAM and
那种在磁盘和DRAM之间
then disks up here you can see at a
那么在这里的磁盘，你可以在看
million nanoseconds that's that's a
亿纳秒就是这样的一个
millisecond so you can see disks are
毫秒，所以你可以看到 磁盘
sort of in this in this sort of
那种在此在这种
millisecond range with access times and
毫秒范围内的存取时间和
those those that they've gone down a
那些他们已经走了下来那些
little bit but not really too much so
点点，但没有真正太多这样
the point I want to make is that there's
我要 说明 一点 的是，有
this huge gap between DRAM
DRAM之间的巨大差距
SSD disk and CPUs and in some cases
SSD硬盘和 CPU，并在某些情况下，
that's even getting worse as time goes
这甚至 变得更糟随着时间的推移
by so that's a problem right how our
通过所以 这是一个 正确的 问题 我们怎么样
programs all need data our data is
程序都需要数据我们的数据是
stored in memory and disk so if our if
存储在内存和磁盘 ，所以如果我们如果
our computers are getting faster and our
我们的电脑正变得越来越快，我们的
storage devices are staying relatively
存储设备是住相对
the same or relatively slower then we've
相同或相对较慢那么我们已经
got a problem right increases in in our
有一个问题，就在增加我们的
in computer performance won't it'll be
在计算机性能不会 它会
hard to make our programs run faster
努力使我们的程序运行得更快
because we'll be limited by the time it
因为我们在时间限制之
takes to to access the data okay so
对需要访问数据 好了，
that's that that's sort of the
这是这是排序 的
fundamental problem that we have to deal
我们必须面对的根本问题
with and it turns out that the key to
用和原来 的关键
bridging this this gap between the CPU
此桥接在CPU之间的这种间隙
and a memory is this is this very basic
和 内存，这是这个非常基本的
fundamental property of programs called
所谓的程序基本属性
locality ok and so this is an essential
当地确定，所以这是一个 重要的
sort of fundamental enduring property of
排序的基本持久性
programs
程式
so we say that done so programs have
所以我们说，这样做的节目有
this property called locality and what
这个属性被称为本地和什么
this means is that I'm sorry I'll just I
这意味着 ，我很 抱歉，我 只是我
have to read it committed it's really
要读它致力于它真的
accurate definition so programs tend to
准确的定义，以便方案往往
use data and instructions whose
使用数据和指令，其
addresses are near or equal to those
地址是接近或等于那些
that they have used recently okay so if
他们使用了最近 好了，所以如果
a program accesses a data item the
程序访问的数据项的
chances are very high that it's going to
机会是非常高的，它的要
access that data item or a nearby data
访问该数据项或附近的数据
item sometime in the near future okay
在不久的将来项目好吗
that likelihood that the program is
该可能性，该方案是
going to access that data item or a
要访问该数据项或
nearby a data item in the near future is
附近 在不久的将来 的某个数据项
this property called locality so well
这个属性被称为本地这么好
this we typically distinguish two two
这一点，我们通常区分 二两
different kinds of locality temporal
不同地区的时间
locality is the property that recently
局部性的财产，最近
referenced items are likely to be
引用的项目很可能是
referenced again in the near future ksdc
在不久的将来再次引用ksdc
so if you read a variable chances are
所以如果你读一个变量 机会
you're going to read that variable again
你会再次读取该变量
for example suppose you're summing into
例如，假设你正在总结 成
a variable inside of a loop each loop
一个循环的每个循环 内的可变
iteration you're going to access that
迭代你要访问
that variable okay spatial locality is
该变量没关系空间局部性
that the tendency for items with nearby
对于与附近项目的倾向
addresses up that items if we access if
解决了的项目，如果我们如果访问
we access one item chances are high
我们访问一个项目几率很高
we're going to access a nearby item okay
我们要进入附近的好项目
so let's look at this little snippet of
所以让我们来看看这个小片段
code and see if we can identify all the
代码，看看我们是否能够识别所有 的
different kinds of locality in this code
不同 地区的这一代码
so we have two different kinds of
所以，我们有两种不同的
references there's data references and
引用有数据引用和
then there's instructions right so we're
再有就是正确的指令所以我们
reading instructions out of memory and
读出指令的内存和
those instructions are referencing data
这些指令引用数据
okay so first of all notice that we're
好了，第一 ，我们是 所有的通知
we're referencing the elements of an
我们引用的元素
array in succession so we're increasing
阵列陆续 所以我们增加
AI by one each time and then we're so
AI通过 一个每次 ，然后 我们是如此
we're incrementing I each each iteration
我们递增我每次每次迭代
through the loop and we're reading AI
通过循环，我们正在阅读AI
okay so
可以，然后呢
is called a stride one reference pattern
被称为步幅一个参考图形
the stride is how much we're
步幅是多少，我们是
incrementing this this index so we're
增加此此指数所以我们
since we're incrementing it by one we
因为我们通过一个我们增加它
call that a stride one pattern so what
调用一个箭步一个模式等什么
kind of what kind of locality is the
一种什么样的地方 的 是
repeated references to AI spatial or
到AI空间重复的引用或
temporal spatial right because we're
时间空间的权利，因为我们是
accessing nearby items okay what about
没关系什么访问有关附近的项目
the referencing this this variable some
在此引用这个变量的一些
inside the loop that's temporal now what
环路， 现在是什么时间内
about instructions so we're we're
有关说明，以便我们我们
referencing where each loop iteration
参考其中每个循环迭代
we're reference we're executing a
我们参考，我们正在执行
sequence of instructions so what kind of
指令序列那么什么样的
locality is that within each loop
局部性的是， 每个环内
iteration
迭代
no that's spatial right because we're
没有这空间的权利，因为我们是
just executing a sequence of
刚刚执行的序列
instructions within each loop iteration
每次循环迭代内的指令
but then we cycle through the loop
但 后来我们 通过循环 周期
repeatedly so we'll chances so each loop
反复所以我们的机会所以每次循环
iteration we're going to access each of
迭代我们要 访问 的每一个
those instructions that we access the
那些我们 访问的说明
previous loop iteration make sure we go
以前的循环迭代确保我们走
up we just keep at we're just going to
我们最多只是不断在我们正要
keep executing the same assembly
继续执行同一程序集
language instructions that implement
实现语言指令
this loop body now in this simple
现在这个循环体，在这个简单
example it's probably just one
例如，它可能只是一个
instruction but in general your loop can
指令，但在一般的循环能
have multiple instructions
有多个指令
now when I claim to you I'm one of the
现在，当我要求你 ，我 的 一个
one of the main sort of points of this
主要种类的这个点中的一个
just this whole course is that as a
只是这整个过程是，作为一个
professional programmer it's an
专业的程序员它是一个
essential skill that that you be able to
那你能够基本技能
look at code and so get a qualitative
看代码，并 因此得到了质
sense of its locality because as we'll
它的地方的意义，因为正如我们将
see
看到
good locality turns into good
好的地方变成好
performance the way that systems are
性能是系统的方式
built these days so as a programmer it's
建这些天，以便作为一个程序员 是
very important for you to be able to
非常重要的，你 要能够 对
kind of look at code and get some
那种看代码，并得到一些
qualitative sense like and that's pretty
定性的感觉一样，这就是漂亮
good locality that's terrible locality
好的地方太可怕了局部性
right that's and what you want to do is
正确的是， 你想要做的是 什么
avoid the terrible locality in your code
避免 在您的代码可怕的地方
so let's look at a simple example here
让我们 来看一个简单的例子 在这里
to see what I mean by this so what I'm
看看我的意思，所以我什么
doing is I'm taking an array a
做的是我正在 一个数组
two-dimensional array a with M M rows
二维阵列的与 行MM
and n columns and within a doubly nested
和n列 和内的双重嵌套
loop iterating on I and J I'm summing
迭代循环对我和J，我总结
the elements of that array
该阵列的元件
it seems this a very simple operation
看来 这是一个非常简单的操作
what could go wrong right so it turns
什么可能出问题的权利，使其变为
out if you write this code to have to
如果你写的代码出有
add locality it'll run order of
加地方它会运行秩序
magnitude slower so just look at this if
幅度较慢所以单看这一点，如果
you look at this do you think this has
你看看这个，你认为这有
good locality or bad locality now let's
好的地方或坏的地方 ，现在让我们
look at the with respect to the accesses
看看关于访问
of a
的
good or bad well so how is how is a laid
好坏以及因此如何是怎么一个悠闲
out in memory right it's row line right
出内存右它的行权行
so see uses used lays out a raised row
所以看到使用用途，勾画出 一个 连续上调
lies so the first all the elements of
谎言所以首先的要素
the first row followed by all the
第一行之后的所有
elements of the second row followed by
第二行的元素， 随后
all the elements of the third row okay
第三行中的所有元素 好吗
so how are we accessing this array look
那么我们如何访问这个数组 的样子
at we're accessing a IJ and we're
在我们访问IJ 和我们
varying J the fastest so we hold eye
改变j中最快的，所以我们保持 眼睛
constant and then we vary J and then we
恒定，然后我们变化J和然后我们
access all so we hold eye constant to
接入都让我们保持眼睛常数
access row I and then we vary J to
一行访问我，然后我们改变J确定
access all the columns in that row okay
访问该 行还行 中的所有列
so each each hitter and then we increase
所以每个每个击球手，然后 我们增加
and then we go back and increase I so
然后我们回去，并增加 我这样
now we're accessing the next row okay so
现在我们所访问的下一行好了，
if we were to look at the addresses of a
如果我们看的地址
IJ the sequence of addresses that are
IJ 是地址 序列
being read those would correspond to a
被读取那些将对应于
stride one access and so we'd be
迈进一个访问，所以我们会很
accessing all the elements those of a
访问所有 的元素的那些的
sequentially in order okay so that's
顺序为了 好了，这就是
really good spatial locality right
真正好的空间 局部性权
that's the best you can do
这就是你能做的最好的
now what about what about and then we
现在怎么样怎么样，然后我们
have temporal locality on some so that's
有时间局部性一些，这样的
good right so everything about this is
良好的权利，使这个一切
pretty good so this is a good case now
相当不错的，所以这 是 一个很好的 案例，现在
what about this what I've done I've
这个东西我做了什么我已经
taken the same program and I've just
采取了同样的计划，我刚刚
inverted the loops so I loop on J first
倒置循环，所以我环J上第一
and then on I and then I just have the
然后在我，然后我只是有
same inner loop body
相同的内循环体
now what does that do to this what does
现在是什么做这做什么
that do to the spatial locality of our
该做的空间局部性 我们
accesses okay yeah terrible because it's
访问还好 耶可怕的 ，因为它是
going you should be offended when you
外出时，你应该被冒犯，当 你
see this isn't awful but it's terrible
看这是不可怕，但它是 可怕的
right because look at so we're now we're
正确的，因为看 所以我们现在是我们
holding Jay
控股周杰伦
we're holding Jay constant and then
我们拿着周杰伦不变，然后
we're iterating through the jth element
我们通过第j个元素迭代
of each row so that's skipping we have n
各行，以便的精选跳绳我们有N
we have n elements in each row so we're
我们有N 每一行 中的元素 ，所以我们是
doing a stride n access through memory
通过 做 存储 一个箭步 -N接入
so we're going like this and then we're
所以我们要像这样，然后我们
incrementing then we're looking then
然后递增，我们正在寻找，然后
we're incrementing the column by one and
我们通过一个递增列
then we're doing this again
那么我们就这样了
so it's terrible spatial locality this
所以这是可怕的空间局部性这
is the worst spatial locality we could
是最糟糕的空间位置，我们可以
get now let's look at a three
现在得到让我们来看看三
dimensional array and let me ask you to
维数组，让我问 你
let me post the following question can
让我张贴以下问题 可
you based on this sort of qualitative
您根据这种定性
idea that this idea that you want you
想法，这种想法，你想你
want to try to get a stride one
想尝试得到 一个箭步一个
reference pattern okay so how would you
参考模式好，所以你会怎样
permute these givenness given this inter
置换这些所予给这 间
body a kij
身体KIJ
how would you promote permute these
你将如何推动这些置换
these loop indices to give a stride one
这些循环指标 给一个箭步一个
reference pattern okay that's right ki
参考模式好没错 き
J's is right so what in general we want
J的是正确的 ，所以我们 希望 在一般什么
to do is we want to go going from right
做的是我们要去 右去
to left we want we want those indices to
向左我们希望，我们希望这些指数来
be changing the fastest so we want J we
要改变最快的，所以我们希望我们Ĵ
want K and I to be held constant and
想K和我将保持恒定和
then we want to change J then we want to
然后我们想 改变J，则我们要
increment I and then for that value that
增加我，然后为值
those values of K and I we want to want
K和 我 的那些价值 ，我们希望要
a sequence through all the values of J
至 J 的所有值的序列
again okay
再次好吗
okay so we've looked at properties of
好了，我们已经看了的性质
Technology of storage technologies and
存储技术和 工艺
what we and there's this sort of basic
我们和有这种基本
sort of fundamental principle that
排序的基本原则
cheaper storage the bigger storage
更便宜的存储 更大的存储
higher capacity storage is cheaper more
更高容量的存储是 更 便宜
expensive storage is smaller because we
昂贵的存储是 因为我们 小
just don't have that we can't spend
只是没有 我们可以不花
enough money there's this gap there's
足够的钱， 还有的这种差距 有
this gap between our storage devices and
我们的存储设备和之间的差距
the CPU that is at least in the case of
的CPU， 其 至少在的情况下
disks are getting bigger and we have
磁盘正在变得更大，我们有
programs that exhibit locality ok so
显示出本地 确定 ，所以计划
these three things these properties of
这三样东西的这些属性
storage technologies and properties of
存储技术和性能
our programs complement each other in
我们的计划相互补充
this beautiful way to suggest and inform
这个美丽的 方式 提出 ，并通知
the design of our storage systems and
我们的存储系统的设计和
this design is something called the
这种设计被称为东西
memory hierarchy ok here's the idea of a
存储层次 确定这里是一个想法
memory hierarchy you layer instead of a
存储层次您层代替
flat memory system you now you create
你现在在创建平面内存系统
your memory system as a hierarchy of
您的存储系统的层次结构
devices and at the top of the at the top
在的顶部的顶部的装置和
of this hierarchy you have your smaller
这个层次的你有你的小
faster and more expensive storage
更快，更昂贵的存储
devices so at the very top you have
设备，以便在 最高层必须
registers which are which can be
寄存器其是其可以是
accessed and within one cycle right one
访问和一个周期内正确的
instruction while that instruction is
指令，而该指令是
executing can access read and write into
执行可以访问读取和写入
a register
寄存器
okay so registers are at the top of the
好了，所以寄存器是在的顶部
hierarchy but because those are in
层次，但因为这些都是在
custom silicon they're very expensive
定制硅他们是非常昂贵的
right the fabrication plants to make
右边的制造工厂，使
processors cost billions of dollars ok
处理器耗资数十亿美元OK
so this is the most expensive and
所以这是最昂贵的，
because of that it's also the smallest
因为它也是最小的
we've only got 16 registers at the top
我们只在顶部有16个寄存器
of the hierarchy now below that we put
现在下面 我们把层次
one or more SRAM memories remember SRAM
一个或多个SRAM存储器SRAM记忆
is faster
是比较快的
it's the fastest kind of memory so we
这是最快的一种记忆，所以我们
put one or more so-called
把一个或 多个 所谓的
caches cache memories built out of SRAM
内置缓存SRAM 进行高速缓存存储器
in the processor chip itself and then
在处理器芯片本身，然后
and these caches because they're made
这些高速缓存，因为它们是由
out of SRAM they're on the order of
从SRAM他们的顺序
megabytes in size okay they're much
在大小兆 还好他们多
bigger than registers but they're
比寄存器大，但他们
they're megabytes okay which if we look
他们兆 好它，如果我们看
and then beneath that is our main memory
然后那 下面 就是我们的主内存
which is built out of DRAM and those can
它内置了DRAM和那些能
be gigabytes tens of gigabytes on on
是千兆字节数十GB的上
modern systems and then below that is
现代系统，然后在下面是
our local disks and we can even have
我们的本地 磁盘，我们甚至可以有
lower layers like web servers that are
下层像web服务器是
storing you know for storing stuff on
存储你知道上存储的东西
google that you can think of that as
谷歌，你能想到的 ，如
just part of our hierarchy now here's
只是 我们 体系 中的 一部分 ，现在这里的
the here's the key idea in a higher
在这里有更高的核心理念
Inlet in a memory hierarchy each level
入口的存储器层次结构中每个级别
in this hierarchy holds data that's
在这个层次结构保存数据这
retrieved from the next lower level
从下一级中检索
okay so caches hold registers hold data
好了，所以缓存保持寄存器保存数据
that's that's stored in the l1 cache the
这是一个的存储在 L1缓存的
l1 cache holds data that's retrieved
L1缓存认为，检索出的数据
from the l2 cache the l3 cache holds
从L2缓存 L3缓存持有
data that's restored that's that's
多数民众赞成恢复的数据是这
retrieved from main memory main memory
从主存储器的主存储器中检索
holds data that's retrieved from
认为这是一个从检索到的数据
secondary disk and so on now
二级盘等，现在
as we'll see the that the reason memory
正如我们即将看到的，之所以记忆
systems are designed like this is that
系统的设计就像 这是
they when you have this kind of system
他们当你有这种 系统
this you can access in general you can
这个你可以在一般的访问可以
access your data at the speed of the
在的速度访问您的 数据
fastest item of the day and at the top
在 顶部 的 一天，最快的项目
of the hierarchy so that's the fastest
层次的所以这是最快的
but with the cost of the storage at the
但随着存储的成本
lower part of the hierarchy okay so this
层次结构的下部好了，所以这
this works all because of an idea called
这个工程全称为一个想法，因为
caching so a cache in compute 2 took it
缓存，以便在计算2高速缓存把它
to a computer scientist is a it's a
一个计算机科学家是它的一个
smaller faster storage device that acts
作用较小的较快的存储设备
as a staging area for the data in a
作为在该数据的分段区域
larger slower device so just like like
较大较慢的设备所以就像像
here you can think of your main memory
在这里你可以认为 你的主内存
is a cache for data that's stored on
是上存储的数据高速缓存
disk right you read memory from disk and
磁盘 对你 从磁盘 读入内存 ，
then you store it in a memory ok you can
那么你将其存储在 确定可以 对存储
think of the main memory as a staging
认为主要的内存作为一个临时的
area so once you get the data from the
区域，这样一旦你 从数据
disk you don't access it again on the
磁盘你不要 再 访问它 的
disk access to the memory which is much
磁盘访问是多少内存
faster ok so this idea propagates all
快好了，所以这个想法的所有传播
the way up the hierarchy ok so we you
一路上扬的层次确定，所以我们为您
can think of a cache on one way to think
可以想到的一种方式想缓存
of a cache is imagine your backpack when
缓存是想像你的背包时，
you're getting ready to come to school
你准备到学校来
in the morning so you're in your
早晨所以你 在你的
apartment which is kind of far away from
公寓这是一种 从 远处
school so before you come into school
学校，所以 你进入学校 之前
you take items from from your house and
你把物品从你的房子 和
you put them in your backpack because
你把它们放在你的背包 ，因为
and then then when and then you walk
然后再当，然后你走
then you come to school if you need
那么你来上学，如果你需要
those items they're in your backpack you
那些 他们 的项目 在您的背包你
know if you didn't do that every time
知道，如果你没有这样做，每次
you needed something you'd have to walk
你需要的东西，你必须走
back home and get it and walk back to
回家， 并把它往回走，到
school
学校
it so the idea of caching is very you
它 使高速缓存的想法是挺你
know it's a very familiar kind of simple
知道这是一个非常熟悉的一种简单
notion but it turns out to be quite
概念，但事实证明是 相当
powerful and it shows up in all parts of
功能强大，它 的 所有部分显示出来
the computer system okay so so what we
没关系 的计算机系统 ， 所以我们
say is that for each level K in the
说的是，在每个等级k
hierarchy the the faster smaller device
层次结构中的更快更小的设备
of level K serves as a cache for the
级别K个用作用于缓存
larger slower device at level K plus-1
在等级k 加1较大较慢的装置
remember our levels go from so L zero
记得我们从水平这么大号零走
it's the highest of the smallest lowest
这是最高的最小最低
level is actually the highest the
实际上水平最高的是
further stuff in the camp in the
在营地进一步东西
hierarchy and as we increase the levels
层次结构，并为我们提高水平
we're going down the hierarchy now why
我们 现在为什么 要去到整个组织
do they work so this is this is a really
做他们的工作，所以这 是这 是一个非常
fundamental idea they work because of
他们因为工作基本理念
locality so because of locality programs
地点是因为本地程序
tend to access data that's stored at
往往访问一个储存的数据
level K more often than they access data
k级往往比他们访问数据
at level K plus-1 okay so if we access
在等级k 加1好了，所以，如果我们访问
an item at level K plus-1 we can move it
在级别k 加1， 我们可以将它的项目
up to level K chances are because of
高达等级k 机会是因为
locality we're going to access it again
局部性我们将再次访问
okay so now we're accessing the data at
好了，现在我们要访问的数据
level K multiple times at the at the
在等级k多次在
rate at the speed of level K not at the
率级 K 的速度 不是在
speed of level k plus one okay so that's
k级速度加 一 好 了，这就是
that's the fun the fundal fundamental
这就是乐趣胃底根本
idea and because because we're not
想法和因为 因为我们不
accessing data at level K plus-1 as
在等级k访问数据 加1作为
often we can we can afford to use slower
通常我们可以，我们能够 用 得起 慢
storage devices which are cheaper okay
存储装置，其是便宜好
in this and thus we can make them bigger
在此，因此，我们可以使他们做大
and cheaper predict so what this does is
便宜预测所以这样做是什么
the hierarchy creates a large pool of
层次创造了一个大水池
storage that's roughly about the size of
存储这大致占规模
the lowest level that can be accessed at
可 在 被 访问 的最低水平。
the speed at the highest level
速度 最高 级别
all right look let's look at how caching
没事看看让我们来看看如何缓存
works in a general way and then we'll
工作在一般的方式，然后我们会
see on Thursday how these hardware cache
看到周四如何将这些硬件缓存
memories work okay but like I said
回忆的工作不错，但就像我说的
caching is a very general idea that can
缓存是一个非常普遍的想法，可以
be applied at all levels in the in the
在各级中的应用
hierarchy so here we have a cache so the
层次所以在这里我们有一个缓存，因此
in all kinds of most caches there's some
在各种最高速缓存的有一些
kind of transfer unit to go from one
一种转印单元从一个去
level to the next so here we have at
到下一级所以在这里我们在
this at this upper level we have a what
这在这个级别上，我们有什么
we'll call the cache that can hold for
我们会打电话， 可保持 高速缓存
blocks so our our memory and then at the
块，这样我们的我们的记忆中，然后在
lower level we have memory and this
较低的水平，我们有记忆，这
memory is partitioned into blocks of
存储器被划分为块
some fixed size that's this that's the
一些固定的大小这是这是这样的
way cache is near the near the upper
路高速靠近 靠近上
part of the hierarchy work now at the
在目前的层级工作的一部分
lower levels like if you're accessing
下级一样，如果你正在访问
data say from a web server then the data
数据从Web服务器然后将 数据说
is partitioned into files typically okay
被分成文件通常好吗
but in other levels the data is
但在其他级别 的数据
partitioned into blocks so just suppose
分块所以只是假设
this is main memory and then above that
这是主存储器中，然后上面
we have a that consists of a bunch of
我们有一个 由一堆的
these blocks so we just take the memory
这些块，所以我们只取记忆
and partition ins blocks where each
和分区INS块，其中每个
block is the same number of bytes and
块是相同的字节数 ，并
then data will be transferred between
然后将数据之间传送
memory and the cache in block size
存储器和 在块大小 的高速缓存
transfer units okay so if you need data
转让单位好，所以如果你需要数据
from the memory if the cache needs data
从内存，如果缓存中 的数据 需要
from the memory it'll grab a whole block
从存储器中它会抓住一个整块
and then at any point in time the cache
然后在时间的缓存中的任何点
holds a subset of the blocks in main
保持在主块的子集
memory okay so this this cache is much
内存好了，所以这个这个缓存是多少
faster but it's also much slower
速度更快，但 它也慢得多
and because of that and it's much
并且因为这和它的多
smaller I'm sorry it's much faster but
小对不起它的速度 更快，但
it's it's much more expensive because
这是它的更昂贵，因为
it's faster it's more expensive and
它的速度更快也更贵，
because it's more expensive it's smaller
因为它更昂贵的 是小
now suppose suppose the cash once that
现在 假设假设 现金 一旦
reference say that the CPU asks for data
参考说，CPU请求数据
that's contained in block four so it
该中都包含的块中有四个因此它
looks it looks to see if the data is in
看起来它查看数据是否 在
the cache it's not so the cache asks the
缓存它不是那么缓存 问
memory to give it block four so that
内存给它块中的四个，这样
block is copied from memory into the
块是从存储器拷贝到
cache overwriting the one of the
缓存覆盖的一
existing in this case block eight it
现有在这种情况下阻止个IT
will overwrite blockade so now now block
将覆盖封锁所以现在现在块
four is in our cache now suppose now now
四是在我们现在的缓存现在假设现在
suppose the CPU s for a some data that's
假设CPU■ 对于一些数据，是
in block ten that gets copied up and and
在块 了 十个 被复制并和
we overwrite that that block now the
我们会覆盖该块现在
whole idea of storing it in the cache is
存储在缓存中 的整体思路 是
that we're hoping that to seek the
那我们希望寻求
program that's executing on the CPU will
这就是CPU上执行的程序将
reuse one of those blocks we just spent
重用，我们刚刚度过的那些块的一个
all the time we went to all this trouble
所有的时间我们去一切麻烦
to copy it from memory to to this cache
把它从 内存 复制 到这个缓存
and we know that's slow so now suppose
我们知道这是缓慢，现在假设
that the CPU needs some data in Block B
该CPU需要 在方框B的一些数据
in this case fourteen okay so it needs
在这种情况下，14好了，所以它需要
it needs the more memory word that's
它需要更多的 内存词是
stored that was originally stored in
存储最初存储在
memory it in block fourteen well now
内存在方框14现在好了
this cache can just return that's what
该缓存可以只返回那是什么
we call a hit right so the block that we
我们所说的一击右 所以块，我们
access is in the cache so that's good
访问是在缓存中，这样的好
hits are good because now we can return
点击率是不错的，因为现在我们可以 返回
that block directly to CTU and this this
该块 直接CTU，这此
memory is much faster than if we had to
内存比，如果我们不得不快得多
go all the way to main memory to the
一路到主 存储器到
DRAM okay so the SRAM much faster than
DRAM 好所以SRAM 比快得多
the DRAM so they see to you gets that
在DRAM 让他们看到你获取
block fourteen much faster than it would
块14比它快得多
have if it just gone all the way to
有，如果它只是走了一路
memory okay these sort of other the the
内存好这些类的 其他 的
opposite of a hit is a Miss so suppose
命中的对面是一个 小姐所以假设
the CPU s for block twelve the cache
该CPU S 表示块12的高速缓存
looks for that block can't find it
查找该块不能找到它
that's a Miss so the the cache has to
这是一个小姐，因此 缓存必须
ask that the main memory of the DRAM for
问DRAM的主 存储器
block twelve where it gets copied into
块12 在那里它被复制到
the cache and then it can return that so
缓存中，然后它可以返回 该如此
that takes longer right so the CT has to
这需要更长的时间正确的，因此 CT 有
wait for that block to be X to be
等待的块为 X是
searched from memory and so misses are
从内存搜索等未命中
slow so hits are good because they're
缓慢，点击率是不错的，因为他们是
fast misses are bad because they're
快速的失误是不好的，因为 他们是
they're slow now we typically
他们现在慢，我们通常
distinguish between several different
几种 不同的区分
kinds of caches so the first kind of
两种缓存所以第一种
miss is a cold miss or a compulsory miss
思念是一种冷小姐或强制 缺失
which is caused because there's just
这导致，因为有刚
nothing in the cache
没有在缓存中
initially caches they're empty they have
最初缓存他们是空的，他们有
no blocks and as we fetch as we fetch
无块，因为我们取为我们取
blocks from the lower level from the
从较低的水平块
next the next level and put them in the
接下来的一个新的水平，并把它们放在
cache the cache will slowly fill up with
缓存缓存会慢慢填满
blocks and we'll get and that will
块，我们会尽快和 意志
increase the likelihood of Hibbs but
增加希布斯的可能性，但
when the cache is empty
当缓存为空
we're going to miss every time right so
我们要每次都错过这样的权利
this there's just no way to avoid cold
这里面还有没有办法来避免 冷
misses right you got a so this is called
想念你的权利得到了所以这个被称为
warming up your cache so as you load
热身缓存以便加载
data items into the cache initially it's
数据项到缓存中最初它是
cold and as you add more items you're
冷，当您添加 更多的项目 你
warming it up meaning that you're
热身它意味着你
increasing the likelihood of a hit now
现在增加一击的可能性
there's a there's another sort of
有一个有另一种形式的
symmetric kind of myth which is called
对称一种神话被称为
the capacity miss and these misses are
在容量 缺失而这些失误是
due to the fact that the cache is just a
由于高速缓存仅仅是一个
certain size right you just can't in the
一定规模的权利，你只是 不能在
example we looked at we only had four
比如我们看，我们只有有四个
blocks so if we're if we're trying if
块，这样如果我们如果我们想，如果
our if our if our temporal locality
我们如果我们的，如果我们的时间局部性
involves eight blocks you know say it's
涉及八个街区，你知道说这是
a loop that we're accessing is is
一个循环，我们要访问的是
accessing elements an array that that
访问元素的数组 那
consists of eight blocks there's just
由八个块有刚
not enough room to store eight blocks
没有足够的空间来存储 八个街区
and therefore block cache so we're going
因此阻止缓存所以我们要
to get
要得到
right we would need a bigger cache to be
正确的，我们需要一个更大的 高速缓存可
able to satisfy and store those eight
能够 满足和存储这 八个
blocks and if we had a big enough cache
块，如果我们有一个足够大的缓存
then we get good hit rate right if we
那么，我们得到很好的命中率的权利，如果我们
could store all the blocks in our cache
可能所有的块存储在我们的缓存
then we then then the cache could take
然后我们再那么缓存可以采取
advantage of the the spatial and
利用的空间的和
temporal locality within that program so
在该 程序 中时间局部性所以
in general what we call this set of
一般我们称这组
blocks at any point in time when a
在任何点块时间当
program is running we call the set of
程序运行我们所说的一套
blocks that are sort of being accessed
这是那种被 访问的块
over and over again the working set and
一遍又一遍的工作集和
so your working set and the working set
所以你的工作组和工作组
will change you know as you go from loop
将改变你知道当你从循环去
to loop from function to function but at
循环从函数的功能，但在
a point in time in your program when it
在时间 程序 中 的一个点时，
you have this idea of a working set
你有这种想法的一个工作组
which is sort of the blocks that you
这是种块的， 你
need to have stored in your cache okay
需要有存储在 缓存好吗
and so when you're working set size
所以当你的工作集大小
exceeds your cache size then you get
超出你的缓存大小，那么你得到
capacity misses there's this other kind
容量缺失有这样其他种类
of weird miss called a conflict miss
奇怪的小姐 叫冲突未
which has to do with the way that caches
其中有与方式 ，缓存做
are often implemented so the idea is
经常执行这样的想法是
that most cash especially hardware
大部分现金尤其是 硬件
caches because they're they have to be
高速缓存，因为他们是他们 必须要
simple they have they limit where a
简单 他们拥有 限制，其中一个
block can be placed to some small set of
块可以被放置到一些小的一组
positions in the cache
高速缓存中的位置
so like one of the simplest models is to
所以像最简单的模型之一是
just take block I can only be placed in
只取块我只能放置在
block I mod the cache size so in our
块I MOD缓存大小所以在 我们的
that that little cache we saw that had
这是小的缓存，我们看到了
four blocks we would take we would take
四大块，我们会采取我们将采取
block I from memory and we would stick
从内存块我， 我们会坚持
it at block I mod 4 so block zero would
它在块I MOD 4故块 零 会
go at block 0 in our cache as would
在去块0 在我们的高速缓存和会
block 4 and as would block 8 block 9
方框4 和作为将阻塞8块9
would go into block 1 in the cache and
将进入块1的高速缓存和
that's
那是
when that happens suppose suppose we use
当出现这种情况假设，假设我们使用
that model so we're going to take block
这种模式 ，所以我们要采取块
I and we're going to put it we can only
我和我们打算把它放在我们只能
place it in the cache at block I mod for
将其放置在高速缓存中块I MOD FOR
now suppose our suppose our reference
现在假设我们假设我们的参考
pattern involves from memory block zero
图案从存储器块零涉及
block four and block eight it's only
块中的四个并阻止个IT只是
three blocks so we have we have enough
三个街区，所以我们 有我们有足够的
room in the cache to store those three
房间的缓存来存储这三个
blocks but because of the way we've
的，因为我们的路块，但
decided to place blocks each block will
决定将块，每个块将
be will evict when we access block four
是 将驱逐当我们访问块中有 四个
it'll go into block zero in the cache
它会进入 零 块 在高速缓存中
when we access block for in the cache
当我们在访问缓存块
it'll overwrite that block and it'll go
它会覆盖该块，它会去
into block zero in the cache and so
到在高速缓存中，因此块零
because of this it's really the access
因为这一点 ， 是真正的 访问
pattern conspiring with the the
图案以阴谋的所述
algorithm that we're using for placing
我们使用用于放置该算法
blocks okay so because of this we have
块行不行，是因为这一点，我们有
plenty of room in the cache but because
充足的空间在缓存中，但由于
of this sort of the access pattern
这种访问模式的
conspiring with the placement algorithm
与放置算法阴谋
we get misses every time we'll see how
我们得到错过每一次，我们将看到如何
we'll see how conflict nurses work in
我们将看到冲突护士是如何工作的
detail when we study your caches
详细当我们研究你的缓存
tomorrow so
所以明天
so this is these caches exist everywhere
所以这是无处不在这些高速缓存
in the memory hierarchy and see all of
在存储层次结构 和看到所有的
them are caches of one form or another
它们是这种或那种形式的高速缓冲存储器
right so you can think of the registers
正确 ，因此您能想到的寄存器
as a type of cache
作为一种类型的高速缓存的
what are they cache for eight byte words
它们是什么缓存八个字节的字
okay where's it cached it's cached
还好这里的IT缓存它的缓存
right on the CPU itself what's the
右边的CPU 本身有什么上
latency it's instant and happens within
等待时间是瞬间发生的内
an instruction and then who manages the
一个指令，然后谁管理
cache
高速缓存
somebody has to manage the cache when
总得有人当管理缓存
when there's a request to load an item
当有加载一个项目的请求
from the lower level in the hierarchy
从层次结构 中 的 下级
something has to decide what to do with
有些事情决定做什么用
that where to put it in the cache that's
但 如把 它放在 这 就是 高速缓存
called managing the cache well in this
所谓在此管理高速缓存以及
case the compiler manages the cache when
情况下，编译管理缓存时
you when you compile your C code the
当您编译C代码
compiler figures out which register data
编译器的数字哪个寄存器中的数据
items from memory are going to go into
从内存中的项目将会进入
okay so good TLB this is something this
好了，好TLB这是后话这个
is a cache that's used in virtual memory
是在虚拟内存使用的高速缓存
then there's these hardware caches
再有就是这些硬件缓存
called l1 and l2 caches so they store 64
所谓的L1和L2缓存，使他们储存64
byte blocks on modern Intel systems and
现代Intel系统字节块和
they're cached on the CPU chip itself in
他们缓存的CPU芯片本身在
in s ramps that are built right into the
在被内置 到 S斜坡
CPU chip and depending on whether l1
CPU芯片和根据 是否L1
caches to on core i7s have a latency of
缓存到核心i7s有一个延迟
4 cycles and l2 has a latency of 10
4个周期 和L2具有10的等待时间
cycles and both of these are managed by
循环，并且这两种由管理
Hardware so when you when the CPU
五金 所以当你在CPU
fetches an item from the l1 cache
从L1 高速缓存 获取项目
Hardware Figg finds it and if there's a
硬件菲格发现它，如果有一个
miss and a block is loaded from l2
未命中和一个块 从L2加载
Hardware in the l1 cache figures out
硬件 L1缓存计算出
where to put it okay so all this is done
把它放在哪里好了，所以这一切完成
without any intervention by Hardware
而无需硬件的任何干预
disks contain buffer operating systems
磁盘包含缓冲操作系统
maintain buffer caches so in this case
保持缓冲区高速缓存所以在这种情况下，
what's cached is portions of files okay
什么是缓存 文件的 部分 好吗
and they're cached in main memory and
他们正在缓存在主内存和
latency to 2 main memory is about a
延迟到2个主要的存储器是大约一个
hundred cycles or so
百次左右
and these are managed by the operating
而这些由 经营管理
system so the operating system reserves
系统，使操作系统储备
the portion of memory to store files
的存储器，用于存储文件的部分
that you've loaded so so the operating
你已经加载，以便使操作
system exploits locality if you if you
系统利用地方，如果你，如果你
read a file and then start reading
读取一个文件，然后开始阅读
referencing bytes from that file it will
从该文件中它会引用字节
actually be served from the file cache
实际上从文件缓存中
and it won't go out to disk network
并且它不会出去磁盘网络
networks maintain caches by things like
通过网络之类的东西保持高速缓存
NFS and SS maintain local caches on disk
NFS 和SS保持在磁盘上的本地缓存
your browser has a cache so when it
您的浏览器有 一个缓存，因此当它
fetches files from from servers it
从服务器获取文件，它
stores those files locally on disk so if
在本地磁盘上保存这些文件，所以如果
you reference those web pages again
再次引用这些网页
they're served from can be local disk
他们是从服务可以是本地磁盘
rather than going all the way across the
而不是 在 将所有的方式
network ok so the point is that these
网络确定这样的一点是，这些
caches exist everywhere in the memory
缓存处处存在于内存
hierarchy and they're all based on the
层次和他们都基于
same principles they're just implemented
他们只是执行相同的原则
in different ways ok so just to
以不同的方式 确定，所以刚
summarize what we've what we've done
总结一下我们已经 我们做了什么
today we've seen that there's there's a
今天我们已经看到，有有一个
gap between the CPU and our storage
CPU 与 我们的 存储 之间的差距
devices that continues to increase
是继续增加设备
we've seen that well-written programs
我们已经看到， 精心编写的程序
have this property called locality and
具有这种性质称为本地 和
we've seen that caching by taking by
我们通过采取看出缓存
using caching we can build a memory
使用高速缓存我们可以建立一个内存
hierarchy that takes advantage of
层次， 它利用优势
locality and programs and allows us to
局部性和程序， 并允许 我们
build storage systems that where we can
构建存储系统在这里我们可以
access data at the rate of the fastest
在 最快 的速度访问数据
device but at the cost and capacity of
设备，但在成本和容量
the devices at the lowest level
在最低 级别 的 设备
ok so Thursday we're going to look at a
确定，所以周四我们要 看看在
very specific part of the hierarchy
层次结构的非常具体的部分
called cache memory
所谓的高速缓存存储器